Guide to the Cooper Square Committee Records TAM.356
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
Cooper Square Committee Records
circa 1960-2009
TAM.356
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
20.0 linear feet in 20 records boxes and one oversized folder
The Cooper Square Community Development Committee and Businessmen’s Association (CSC) is a nonprofit tenant rights and arts advocacy group for residents of New York City’s Lower Eastside that provides social services, including tenant counseling and eviction prevention, and works on community development issues. The organization’s aims are to preserve economic and ethnic diversity in the neighborhood and to contribute to the preservation and development of affordable, environmentally-friendly housing and community/cultural spaces. Records and document types in this collection include minutes, reports, correspondence, memoranda, leafletls, petitions, permits, surveys, reports, and grant proposals.
Cooper Square Committee.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
An agreement donating its records to Tamiment was signed by the Cooper Square Committee in 2006; the first accession of records themselves may have been delivered to Tamiment as early as 1986; another accession arrived in 2015, via Joyce Ravitz, the chairperson of the Committee's Board. The accession numbers associated with these materials are 1986.033 and 2015.001.
Arrangement
The materials have not been arranged by an archivist, but have been retained in the order in which they were received (no apparent system of arrangement).
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Scope and Content Note
Records and document types in this collection include minutes, reports, correspondence, memoranda, leafletls, petitions, permits, surveys, reports, and grant proposals.
Historical/Biographical Note
The Cooper Square Community Development Committee and Businessmen’s Association (CSC) is a nonprofit tenant rights and arts advocacy group for residents of New York City’s Lower Eastside that provides social services, including tenant counseling and eviction prevention, and works on community development issues. The organization’s aims are to preserve economic and ethnic diversity in the neighborhood and to contribute to the preservation and development of affordable, environmentally-friendly housing and community/cultural spaces.
The Committee, which has described itself as “the nation's oldest anti-displacement organization,” was founded in 1959 (then named the Cooper Square Community Development Committee), for the purpose of opposing the City of New York’s urban renewal plan for the Lower Eastside led the City’s Slum Clearance Committee (chaired by “master builder” Robert Moses). CSC’s founders or those involved in the early stages of the organization included Thelma Burdick, Frances Goldin, Esther Rand, Staughton Lynd, and Walter Thabit.
Throughout the 1960’s, the Committee built coalitions, held demonstrations and CSC representatives and members spoke at public meetings. CSC also created an alternative plan to New York City’s original proposals for redevelopment of the Lower Eastside. “The Alternate Plan,” was a community-based plan (used as a model by many other rights organizations since its creation). Its basic principles were that during development displacement must be minimized, must be carried out in stages, and site tenants must have first priority for the housing that is built. On February 13, 1970 CSC’s Alternate Plan was adopted as the official plan of the City of New York. According to Committee’s own online history, the adoption of the Alternate Plan resulted in the preservation of over 300 buildings, and prevented the displacement of several thousand people, including families, senior citizens, artists and art organizations.
In the 1970s the Cooper Square Committee worked to develop community leadership on the Lower East Side, organizing the Bowery Residents Committee, the Good Food Co-op, Third Avenue Artists, and also helped start several tenant rights associations to preserve affordable housing. In the 1980s the CSC sponsored development of the Thelma Burdick Building an apartment building for low-income households at 10 Stanton Street, supported a private development of senior citizen housing on 5th Street and the Bowery and attempted to ensure that it would be a racially-integrated building; created a Revised Plan for the Cooper Square Urban Renewal Area that emphasized renovation of city-owned tenements and loft buildings, preservation of affordable housing and new construction of mixed income housing; helped to persuade the New York City Department of Housing Preservation and Development to approve the development of the 22-unit building for formerly homeless families, to serve as a model for similar projects. The ”Cube Building” is believed to be the first cooperative residence for homeless families in the United States. In the 1990s the organization found itself in the position of becoming a developer itself, in part, when it signed a Memorandum of Understanding with the City of New York, under which the CSC sponsored the renovation of the 22 buildings costing more than $20 million (completed in 2006), and founded the Cooper Square Mutual Housing Association that now manages 356 apartments in 22 formerly city-owned buildings.
In the 2000s the Cooper Square Committee began organizing cultural groups on East 4th Street to develop a plan for disposition of 4 city-owned cultural buildings and vacant buildings and vacant lots in the neighborhood. Planning efforts culminated in the sale of the city-owned properties to the cultural groups in 2005. Development of the Cooper Square Urban Renewal Area was largely completed by 2008. CSC reported that 846 of the 1,377 new and renovated apartments were low income units (61% of the total) and that the sites contained over 100,000 sq. ft. of cultural space on East 4th Street and 40,000 sq. ft. of recreational space.
In the 2010s the Cooper Square Committee provides housing counseling and social services to area residents; it reaches out to assist low income buildings needing energy efficiency upgrades and works to identify opportunities to develop low/moderate or middle income housing as well as community/cultural spaces on the Lower East Side. It has also launched projects addressing the lack of accessible housing and public accommodations for disabled citizens, is partnering with another organization to renovate a building for homeless lesbian, gay, bi-sexual and transgender (LGBT) youths, and has initiated a Tenant Rights Walking Tour of the Lower Eastside.
Bibliography
Information for this guide was drawn in part from the website for the Cooper Square Committee https://coopersquare.org/ and from:
The Cooper Square Plan; Smoothing the Path to Redevelopment. Oser, Alan S. New York Times, 27 Jan 1991, p. A.5.
Derelict Shell Becomes Co-op For Homeless. McFadden, Robert D. New York Times, 15 Nov 1988, p. B.1.
The Tenant-as-Landlord Movement. Lueck, Thomas J. New York Times, 02 July 1989, p. A.1.
Ravitz, Joyce, Chairperson (aka President) - Board of Cooper Square Committee; Low-income housing.; Tenants’ associations.
- Records
  - Cooper Square Committee Files, 1970s (Box 1)
  - Cooper Square Committee files; Chinese Preservation meeting; Spanish Preservation meeting; Site Action, 1970s (Box 2)
  - Cooper Square Committee: Housing Code Enforcement, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Cooper Square Committee: Of interest to arts committee, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Cooper Square Committee: Arts Committee of Cooper Square, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Cooper Square artists interview, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Cooper Square Committee: Old list of site artists, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Cooper Square Committee: Artists' statements (August 13, 1969 to February 13, 1970), 1969-1970 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Cooper Square Committee: SOHO: Loft conversion, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Cooper Square Committee: Westbeth, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Cooper Square Committee: La Mama, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Cooper Square Committee: National Register of Historic Places, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Cooper Square Committee: National Trust, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Cooper Square Committee: Blank Survey: CETA, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Cooper Square Committee: Landmarks Conservancy, undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Cooper Square Committee: Landmarks: Survey/Information, undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Cooper Square Committee: Steering Committee minutes, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Cooper Square Committee: NY Council for the Humanities, undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Cooper Square Committee: Building Structure Inventory Forms, undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Cooper Square Committee: Historical Research Forms, undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Cooper Square Committee: Inner City Ventures Fund Preliminary Application, undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Cooper Square Committee: New Wilderness Foundation, undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Cooper Square Committee: Attachments, undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Cooper Square Committee: Cooper Square Plans 1969-1982, undated (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Cooper Square Committee: Police permits: Blanks, receipts and copies, 1964-1970, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Cooper Square Committee: Negotiating Committee, 1990-1998 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Cooper Square Committee: Rehabilitation survey, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Cooper Square Committee: Public housing: Cooper Square, 1963-1970 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Cooper Square Committee: Letter re: Rental agreements, filled vacancies, May 17, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Cooper Square Committee: Rent Strike Material: 23 East Third Street, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Cooper Square Committee: Resumes for Cooper Square, 1970-1971 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Cooper Square Committee: Steering Committee minutes, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Cooper Square Committee: Reports to the Steering Committee, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Cooper Square Committee: Steering Committee reports, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Cooper Square Community Development Committee: Minutes and other documents, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Cooper Square Committee: Outgoing Mail, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Cooper Square Committee: Incoming Mail, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Cooper Square Committee: Steering Committee minutes, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Unprocessed Cooper Square Committee documents, 1981-2005 (Box 4)
    Scope and Content Note
    Includes: Photographs; Cooper Square Committee Steering Committee election ballots (1984, 1987, 1992); CSC Neighborhood Preservation Program (2000); Financial statements (2000); Staff attendance books (1981-2000); Cooper Square Committee publications: Thelma Burdick: From the Heart(1990) Cooper Square Committee Forty-Fifth Anniversary and Gala, 1959-2004 (2004); Cooper Square Committee "housewarming" party( 2005); Cooper Square Committee Chronolog y(2005)
  - Security posters (Spanish and English) and anything else about security (memos, etc.), undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Security deposits action, 1971-1972 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Site action minutes, 1973-1974 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Site office, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Site occupancy record cards, undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Simon's group, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Show cause order (CPC), undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Third Avenue Rezoning, 1969-1970 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Thirteenth Street Squatters, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Traffic Department, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - 1971Trees (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Al Upton, 95 East Houston Street, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Urban Development Corporation (UDC), undated (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Coastal Properties, undated (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Blanks, undated (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Neighborhood Preservation Program survey, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Cooper Square Committee documents, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Pagan's Girls Club, undated (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Dutch Interns, undated (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - ANHD / Housing Justice Campaign / 236 West Twenty-Seventh Street, undated (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - 13 East Third Street, undated (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Hernandez, William: 60 East Fourth Street, Apartment 2, undated (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Cooper Square Budget (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Salvation Army Drop-in Center, undated (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Cooper Square Membership Meeting (November 30, 1994), Nov 1994 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Lower East Side Squatters: Garden of Eden, undated (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Community Access, undated (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Pagan, Antonio, undated (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - M. of A.: Methodist, Sponsorship, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Song Sheets, undated (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Esperanza, 1970-1971 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Official Documents (January 7, 1970), Jan 1970 (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Stage 1 Plans, undated (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Di Donato, Luigi, 1967-1968 (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Courthouse Site, 1968-1971 (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - CURMCO, undated (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - Davis, Edmond, Attorney-at-law, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - Housing and Development Authority, 1970-1971 (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Cooper Square: Tenant's application for decrease in rent (32-4-S), undated (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - Letter to New York Times(July 19, 1971), Jul 1971 (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - Early Action Program Planning 1969 (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - Welfare Advice, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - Tenant Information, undated (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - Tenant Compliance Committee, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - Tenant Committee for Fourth Street, undated (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - Squatters, undated (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Stage 1, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - Statistical breakdown for Urban Development Corporation (UDC), 1973 (Box 5, Folder 48)
  - Women's Building, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - St. Mark's Committee, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - St. Mark's building analysis, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 51)
  - Sponsors: Building, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 52)
  - De Salvio, Louis, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 53)
  - Digest: Alternate plan, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 54)
  - Rent strike: 23 East Third Street, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 55)
  - Survey data, 1968 (Box 5, Folder 56)
  - Statements on Cooper Square, 1963-1964 (Box 5, Folder 57)
  - Special events, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 58)
  - Statements at hearings, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 59)
  - Documents from city housing agencies, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 60)
  - Press clippings and releases, 1966-1970 (Box 5, Folder 61)
  - Dispossess Notices, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Thirty day notice, undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Tenants Paying Increases, undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Petitions re: Commercial rent increase, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Rent increase survey and fact sheet, Sep 1977 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Cooper Square Election Material, undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Barretto, Carmen, undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Subway Passes, undated (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Pohani Association, Inc., undated (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Assets Consulting Group, undated (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Bank Resolutions, 1992 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Thelma Burdick Tenants / Hall rental, undated (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Summer festival, 1990 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Bank Resolution, 1998 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Site Action Minutes, 1988-1989 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Support Services: Cube Building, undated (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - William Viera, undated (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Steering Committee Correspondence, undated (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Cube Building Watch, undated (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Cube Work, 1996 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Cooper Square Committee, 1993 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Cooper Square Committee and Cooper Square Mutual Housing Association Relations, 1993 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Bank Resolution, 1993 (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Neighborhood Preservation Program (NPP) Financial Report, 1989-1993 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Neighborhood Preservation Program (NPP) Financial Report, 1993-1995 (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Neighborhood Preservation Program (NPP) Financial Report, 1995-1996 (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Neighborhood Preservation Program (NPP) Financial Report, 1999-2002 (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - (Cooper Square Committee Steering Committee) Minutes, 1998 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Housing Preservation and Development (HPD), 2000 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Computer Repairs, undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Jobs Fair Expenses, Insurance, undated (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Bank resolutions: Forms and Draft, undated (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Bell Atlantic: Bonus Statements, undated (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Payroll and timesheets, undated (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Bank Resolution, 1996 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Bank Resolution, undated (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Legalization of Tenants, undated (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Memos from Coordinating meetings/Daniel Grulich, undated (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Construction Monitor Contract, undated (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Mutual Housing Association Meeting Minutes, undated (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Supers, undated (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Supers, undated (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Low Flush Toilets, undated (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Fuller/PRC Construction, undated (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Masonry Specs Site 4 and 5, undated (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Rehabilitation Process, undated (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Mutual Housing Association, undated (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Management Company, undated (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Proposed Budget for Cooper Square Mutual Housing Association, undated (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Relocation resources: Off/On site, undated (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Apartments, Vacant: Legal cases, Nov 1990 (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - Residential/Commercial Tenants, undated (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - Criteria for Legalization, undated (Box 7, Folder 26)
  - Relocated Tenants, undated (Box 7, Folder 27)
  - 58 and 60 East Fourth Street (September 11, 1991), Sep 1991 (Box 7, Folder 28)
  - Damp/Apartment Surveys, undated (Box 7, Folder 29)
  - Tenant Profiles (Needs), undated (Box 7, Folder 30)
  - Phasing of Rehabilitation (Mutual Housing Association), undated (Box 7, Folder 31)
  - Meeting with Stiller (March 6, 1993), Mar 1993 (Box 7, Folder 32)
  - Unprocessed Cooper Square Committee materials, 1980s-1990s (Box 8)
    Includes: Steering Committee minutes (1980s); materials on Public Housing Speak-Out (April 26, 1997), Cooper Square Committee meetings, quality housing zoning regulations, New Plan for Cooper Square Housing Preservation and Development (HPD) Urban Renewal Area Survey.
  - Unprocessed Cooper Square Committee materials, 1973-1976, 1980s (Box 9)
    Foldered and loose materials that include Steering Committee minutes and reports (1973-1976) and Mutual Housing Association documents (1980s).
  - Unprocessed Cooper Square Committee materials, 1973-1983 (Box 10)
    Includes Steering Committee minutes and reports.
  - Unprocessed Cooper Square Committee materials, 1980s (Box 11)
    Includes Steering Committee minutes and reports (1984-1989) and Membership Committee election material (1980s).
  - MCH and Cooper Square Committee files, Including:Cooper Square Committee Steering Committee Elections: June 26, 1986 and May 25, 1988; Employee evaluations and personnel documents (1980s), 1970s-1980s (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Cooper Square Committee Steering Committee Director's File, undated (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Cooper Square Committee Steering Committee Elections (June 26, 1986) (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Cooper Square Committee Steering Committee Elections (May 25, 1988) (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Housing Preservation and Development (HPD) Community Consultant Program (October 1986 to June 1987), 1986-1987 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Resumes, undated (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Resumes, undated (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - House Personnel, undated (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - House Personnel, 1986 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Arts Committee, 1979 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Stripping, 1979 (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Meeting with Housing Preservation and Development (HPD) Central Office, 1978 (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - House Personnel and Staff Meetings, 1978 (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - Grant proposals for Summer Festival, 1979 (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - Newsletter Copy Volume 4, Number 2, Mar 1979 (Box 12, Folder 16)
  - Rental Agreement and Relevant Correspondence, undated (Box 12, Folder 17)
  - Outgoing Correspondence with Commissioner Nathan Leventhal, 1978 (Box 12, Folder 18)
  - Leaflets, 1981-1982 (Box 12, Folder 19)
  - Housing Preservation and Development (HPD) Correspondence, 1978-1979 (Box 12, Folder 20)
  - Joint Planning Council (JPC) Literature, 1981-1982 (Box 12, Folder 21)
  - Estimate for Sealing, 71 East Fourth Street, 1978 (Box 12, Folder 22)
  - To Be Read, undated (Box 12, Folder 23)
  - Cube, undated (Box 12, Folder 24)
  - Joint Planning Council (JPC), undated (Box 12, Folder 25)
  - Lower East Side Tour, undated (Box 12, Folder 26)
  - National Cooperative Bank, 1988 (Box 12, Folder 27)
  - Cooper Square Plan News Articles, undated (Box 12, Folder 28)
  - AT&T Phone Service, undated (Box 12, Folder 29)
  - Cooper Square Committee Steering Committee Minutes, 1988 (Box 12, Folder 30)
  - Cooper Square Committee Steering Committee Minutes, 1987 (Box 12, Folder 31)
  - HUD Section S Regulations, undated (Box 12, Folder 32)
  - Unidentified File, undated (Box 12, Folder 33)
  - Unidentified Cooper Square Committee File, undated (Box 12, Folder 34)
  - Senior Affairs Committee, undated (Box 12, Folder 35)
  - Membership letter (Spanish), undated (Box 12, Folder 36)
  - Membership letter (English), undated (Box 12, Folder 37)
  - Unprocessed Cooper Square Committee materials, 1980s-1990s (Box 13)
    Foldered and loose documents, including: Meeting minutes; Oddlettes; materials concerning Cube building;, Steering Committee, Mutual Housing Authority (MHA) Buildings 29 East Second Street, Non-MHA buildings 59-61 East Fourth Street, Cooper Union Floor plans GLM information.
  - Unprocessed Cooper Square Committee materials, 1960s (Box 14)
    Foldered and loose materials including news clippings and leaflets (1965), photographs, staff manual.
  - Unprocessed Cooper Square Committee materials, 1970s-1990s (Box 15)
    Unfoldered, loose materials.
  - Unprocessed Cooper Square Materials (Box 16)
  - Unprocessed Cooper Square Materials (Box 17)
  - Unprocessed Cooper Square Materials (Box 18)
  - Unprocessed Cooper Square Materials (Box 19)
  - Unprocessed Cooper Square Materials (Box 20)
  - Oversized Cartoon and Fan, circa 1998 (Flat-file 6, Drawer 15)
- Archived Website, Mar 10, 2012-ongoing
  The Cooper Square Committee (CSC), is a housing association of the Lower East Side, which works with area residents to contribute to the preservation and development of affordable, environmentally-friendly housing and community/cultural spaces. It provides housing and social services, including tenant counseling and eviction prevention; community and tenant organizing; social services and referrals; and community development. The website contains news updates, tenant rights resources, and project information.